<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Marketing | YPlan Tech]]></title>
  <link href="http://YPlan.github.com/blog/categories/marketing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://YPlan.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-29T17:10:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://YPlan.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[YPlan]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stephen Fry Effect]]></title>
    <link href="http://YPlan.github.com/blog/2012/12/20/stephen-fry-effect/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-20T13:29:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://YPlan.github.com/blog/2012/12/20/stephen-fry-effect</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/2012-12-20-stephen-fry-effect/tweet.png"></p>

<p>On the 13th of December 2012, 9:34am GMT we've received a <a href="https://twitter.com/stephenfry/status/279157424642994177">tweet</a>
from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Fry">Stephen Fry</a>. At that point he had 5.1 million followers, making him <a href="http://twitaholic.com/top100/followers/">#5 most followed person in
UK</a>. Here's what happened.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>What's YPlan again?</h3>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/2012-12-20-stephen-fry-effect/app.png" title="YPlan app screenshot" ></p>

<p><a href="https://yplanapp.com">YPlan</a> is an early stage mobile-commerce <a href="https://yplanapp.com">startup</a> based in London.
It's a mobile app which enables Londoners to finally discover, book and go to tonight’s best events in just two taps.
We've been building it mobile-first because of a massive consumer shift towards smartphones
and away from personal computers. One big problem with mobile-first approach is customer acquisition.
It's really difficult for a customer to discover you, moreover he has to go through additional
steps to find you (again) on her/his mobile device, download your app, register, etc.</p>

<p>Given a small advertising budget any ways of reaching people and sending message across are very valuable,
especially if customers read it primarily on their mobile device. Twitter is one of such channels
and we've been very lucky to get Stephen Fry tweet about us.</p>

<h3>Who is Stephen Fry?</h3>

<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Fry">Stephen Fry</a> is an English actor, screenwriter, author, playwright,
journalist, poet, comedian, television presenter and film director. He has been described as a national treasure
who has "enhanced our lives" by the Prince of Wales as he was honoured at the <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/tvandradio/7039549/Stephen-Fry-is-a-national-treasure-says-Prince-Charles.html">National Television
Awards 2010</a>.
Stephen Fry is a self-confessed technology geek, lately running <a href="http://www.channel4.com/programmes/stephen-fry-gadget-man">Gadget Man</a> on Channel 4, so
any tech endorsement he makes carries a big weight. He's got such authority and influence on Twitter
that quite often his messages crash websites that he links to
because of the volume of traffic generated by his large number of followers.</p>

<h3>How did we get him to tweet</h3>

<p>We've reached out to Stephen Fry through his PA, chances of him picking this up were very low. Neveretheless
he got interested in what we do, especially given his background in entertainment sector and his interest
in technology and mobile apps, and invited us for lunch. It went very well, we've explained our thinking
behind YPlan and overall trends behind mobile commerce and <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/bruceupbin/2012/12/14/winners-and-losers-in-the-last-second-economy/">last-second economy</a>.
Stephen Fry is very much on top of what's happening in consumer technology and had a bunch of interesting ideas and suggestions about
improving YPlan. He really liked what we do, especially because we're building a solution to a very real problem,
and promised to tweet about us at some point.</p>

<h3>What's our technology stack</h3>

<p>We're running Python/Django as our backend stack. It runs on <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/">Amazon Web Services</a> using
CloudFormation as described in a post by Julius <a href="/blog/2012/12/05/reusable-infrastructure-the-aws-cloudformation-way/">here</a>.
Most of the static web content is hosted on CloudFront CDN. We're tracking health of our backend servers with <a href="http://newrelic.com">New Relic</a>.
Knowing that such tweets can bring servers down we were a bit nervous and were running with at least 3 High-CPU Medium instances.</p>

<h3>What was the impact</h3>

<p>The tweet came out next day in the morning, it was completely unprompted and did take us by surprise.
It didn't include any direct links, just YPlan name and text endorsing it. I've noticed it directly in my twitter stream.
First thing I've checked was Google Analytics. There was a healthy amount of
traffic, mostly from search. However since our site is mostly static and served off CDN all was fine.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2012-12-20-stephen-fry-effect/ga.png" title="Google Analytics Real-Time" ></p>

<p>The next step was to see what's happening on our API servers when people start downloading the app and start running it. We've got to
around API 80 requests per minute which went down to 50 rpm and stayed such for a few hours. Servers didn't even break
a sweat, both latency and Apdex score stayed the same.</p>

<p><img src="/images/2012-12-20-stephen-fry-effect/newrelic.png" title="New Relic backend API server load" ></p>

<p>The tweet itself got 157 retweets, received 160 favorites and a bunch of replies.</p>

<p>It was difficult to estimate number of downloads real-time, however we shot-up to number 14 in Lifestyle category within
half an hour. Looking at downloads for that day later on we could safely estimate it brought in around 2,000 downloads.
That in itself is very helpful and valuable, because these are high quality and engaged customers.</p>

<p>However the biggest impact was the tremendous amount of publicity and emails we've received. We've got a bunch of emails
from different event organizers and venues willing to work with us, major smartphone manufacturers willing to port YPlan
to their platform as well as tons of supportive emails from our new customers.</p>

<h3>What's next</h3>

<p>Receiving endorsement from such renowned person as Stephen Fry is very pleasing. Our technology stack held up
very well without any noticeable problems or slowdowns. Most importantly it encourages us to continue working
on mobile commerce technology helping consumers and changing entertainment industry for the better.</p>

<blockquote><p><em>Fellow HN readers, please upvote <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5787093">here</a>.</em></p>

<p><em>Oh and by the way, we're <a href="http://yplan.theresumator.com/">hiring</a>!</em></p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
